Openness. It's a word that
الإنفتاح كلمة
denotes opportunity and possibilities.
تدل على الفرص و الإحتمالات.
Open-ended, open hearth,
قضية مفتوحة ، موقد مفتوح
open source, open door policy,
المصدر المفتوح ، سياسة الباب المفتوح
open bar. (Laughter)
الحانة المفتوحة. (ضحك)
And everywhere the world is opening up,
العالم ينفتح في كل مكان،
and it's a good thing.
وهذا أمرٌ جيد.
Why is this happening?
لماذا يحدث هذا؟
The technology revolution is opening the world.
الثورة التقنية تؤدي إلى انفتاح العالم.
Yesterday's Internet was a platform
في الماضي كان الإنترنت منصة
for the presentation of content.
لعرض المحتوى.
The Internet of today is a platform for computation.
الإنترنت في الوقت الحاضر هو منصة للحوسبة.
The Internet is becoming a giant
أصبح الإنترنت حاسوب
global computer, and every time you go on it,
عالمي عملاق ، وفي كل مرة تعمل عليه
you upload a video, you do a Google search,
تقوم برفع فيديو ، أو تبحث في قوقل
you remix something,
أو تدمج بعض الإيقاعات الموسيقية
you're programming this big global computer
أنت تقوم ببرمجة هذا الحاسوب العالمي العملاق
that we all share.
الذي نتشاركه جميعاً.
Humanity is building a machine,
الإنسانية تبني الآلة،
and this enables us to collaborate in new ways.
وهذا يتيح لنا التعاون بطرق جديدة.
Collaboration can occur on
التعاون يمكن أن يحدث على
an astronomical basis.
نطاق هائل.
Now a new generation is opening up the world as well.
جيل جديد الآن ينفتح على العالم كذلك.
I started studying kids about 15 years ago,
أجريت دراسة على الأطفال منذ حوالي 15 عاماً
-- so actually 20 years ago now --
-- في الواقع منذ عشرين عاماً --
and I noticed how my own children were
و قد لاحظت كيف كان أطفالي
effortlessly able to use all this sophisticated technology,
يستخدمون كل هذه التقنية المتطورة بدون صعوبة،
and at first I thought,
في البداية قلت:
"My children are prodigies!" (Laughter)
" أطفالي عباقرة! " (ضحك)
But then I noticed all their friends were like them,
لكن لاحظت لاحقاً أن جميع أصدقائهم كانوا مثلهم،
so that was a bad theory.
لهذا كان ذلك رأيٌ باطل.
So I've started working with a few hundred kids,
لذا بدأت أعمل مع بضع مئات من الأطفال،
and I came to the conclusion
و توصلت إلى نتيجة تُظهر أن
that this is the first generation to come of age
هذا الجيل هو أول جيل يبلغ سن الرشد
in the digital age,
في العصر الرقمي،
to be bathed in bits.
أول جيل يكون محاطاً بالوسائل الرقمية منذ الولادة.
I call them the Net Generation.
أسميهم بجيل الشبكة الرقمية.
I said, these kids are different.
قلت، أولئك الأطفال مختلفون.
They have no fear of technology, because it's not there.
لا يخافون من التقنية ، لأنه لاشيء يستدعي الخوف
It's like the air.
إنها مثل الهواء.
It's sort of like, I have no fear of a refrigerator.
هو نوعاً ما مثل قول ، أنا لا أخاف من الثلاجة.
And — (Laughter)
و - (ضحك)
And there's no more powerful force to change
لا يوجد قوة لتغيير كل المؤسسات
every institution than the first generation of digital natives.
أقوى من الجيل الأول من المواطنين الرقميين.
I'm a digital immigrant.
أنا مهاجر رقمي.
I had to learn the language.
كان علي أن أتعلم اللغة (الجديدة) .
The global economic crisis is opening up the world as well.
الأزمة الإقتصادية العالمية تؤدي إلى الإنفتاح العالمي كذلك.
Our opaque institutions from the Industrial Age,
مؤسساتنا الباهتة من العصر الصناعي,
everything from old models of the corporation,
كل شيء بدءاً من النماذج القديمة للشركات,
government, media, Wall Street,
الحكومة ، الإعلام ، وول ستريت
are in various stages of being stalled or frozen
تمر بمراحل متنوعة لأن تكون في مرحلة التوقف أو التجمد
or in atrophy or even failing,
أو في مرحلة الضمور أو حتى الفشل.
and this is now creating a burning platform in the world.
وهذا الآن يجعل العالم يقف على " منصة تحترق ".
I mean, think about Wall Street.
أعني ، فكروا بـ وول ستريت.
The core modus operandi of Wall Street almost brought down
طريقة العمل الأساسية في وول ستريت أسقطت تقريباً
global capitalism.
الرأسمالية العالمية.
Now, you know the idea of a burning platform,
الآن, أنتم تعرفون فكرة " المنصة المحترقة "،
that you're somewhere where the costs of staying where you are
أن تكون في وضع ما حيث يكون ثمن البقاء فيه
become greater than the costs of moving to something different,
أكبر من ثمن الإنتقال إلى وضع آخر مختلف،
perhaps something radically different.
ربما يكون وضع مختلف اختلاف جذري.
And we need to change
و نحن نحتاج إلى تغيير
and open up all of our institutions.
و أن نفتح كل مؤسساتنا.
So this technology push,
إذن دفع التكنولوجيا هذا,
a demographic kick from a new generation
الركلة الديموغرافية من الجيل جديد
and a demand pull from a new
و جاذبية السوق من البيئة
economic global environment
الإقتصادية العالمية الجديدة
is causing the world to open up.
يؤدي كل منهما إلى انفتاح العالم.
Now, I think, in fact,
الآن، أعتقد ، في الحقيقة
we're at a turning point in human history,
إننا نقف عند نقطة تحول في التاريخ البشري،
where we can finally now rebuild
حيث يمكننا أخيراً إعادة بناء
many of the institutions of the Industrial Age
العديد من مؤسسات العصر الصناعي
around a new set of principles.
حول مجموعة جديدة من المبادئ.
Now, what is openness?
الآن، ماهو الإنفتاح؟
Well, as it turns out, openness
حسناً، كما يتبين ، للإنفتاح
has a number of different meanings,
عدد من المعاني المختلفة
and for each there's a corresponding principle
و لكل معنى مبدأ متماشي
for the transformation of
مع تحوّل
civilization.
الحضارة.
The first is collaboration.
المعنى الأول هو التعاون.
Now, this is openness in the sense of the boundaries
و هنا يكون الإنفتاح بمعنى أن تكون الحواجز
of organizations becoming more porous and fluid
بين المنظمات أكثر قابلية للإختراق
and open.
و الإنفتاح.
The guy in the picture here,
الشخص في هذه الصورة هنا،
I'll tell you his story.
سأخبركم عن قصته.
His name is Rob McEwen.
اسمه روب ماكيوين.
I'd like to say, "I have this think tank, we scour the world
أود أن أقول " لدي مركز البحث هذا ، نحن نطوف العالم
for amazing case studies."
من أجل القيام بدراسات لحالات إستثنائية."
The reason I know this story
أنا أعرف عن القصة
is because he's my neighbor. (Laughter)
لأنه جاري. (ضحك)
He actually moved across the street from us,
في الواقع لقد انتقل إلى الشارع القريب منا
and he held a cocktail party
و أقام حفلة كوكتيل
to meet the neighbors, and he says, "You're Don Tapscott.
ليلتقي بالجيران، وقال: " أنت دون تابسكوت.
I've read some of your books."
لقد قرأت بعضاً من كتابك."
I said, "Great. What do you do?"
قلت: " هذا رائع. ماذا تعمل؟"
And he says, "Well I used to be a banker
و قال: " كنت مصرفيّ
and now I'm a gold miner."
و الآن أنا أعمل في منجم ذهب."
And he tells me this amazing story.
ثم أخبرني هذه القصة الرائعة.
He takes over this gold mine, and his geologists
يقوم هو بإدارة منجم الذهب، و من يعمل معه من الجيولوجيين
can't tell him where the gold is.
لم يتمكنوا من إخباره عن مكان الذهب.
He gives them more money for geological data,
يعطيهم المزيد من المال من أجل البيانات الجيولوجية،
they come back, they can't tell
يعودون إليه، و لا يتمكنون من اخباره
him where to go into production.
عن مكان توفره.
After a few years, he's so frustrated he's ready
بعد بضع سنوات، كان محبطاً حتى كاد أن يستسلم
to give up, but he has an epiphany one day.
لكنه في أحد الأيام تنبه فجأة إلى شيء ما.
He wonders, "If my geologists don't know where the gold is,
تسائل," إن كان عمالي الجيولوجيين لا يعلمون عن مكان وجود الذهب،
maybe somebody else does."
ربما يعرف مكانه أشخاص آخرين."
So he does a "radical" thing.
ثم فعل شيئاً " جذرياً " .
He takes his geological data,
أخذ بياناته الجيولوجية
he publishes it and he holds a contest on the Internet
ثم قام بنشرها و أقام مسابقة على الإنترنت
called the Goldcorp Challenge.
أسماها بـ تحدي قولدكورب.
It's basically half a million dollars in prize money
و هي في الأساس، جائزة نقدية بقيمة نصف مليون دولار
for anybody who can tell me, do I have any gold,
لأي شخص يستطيع اخباري إن كان لدي ذهب,
and if so, where is it? (Laughter)
و إن كان لدي، أين هو؟ (ضحك)
He gets submissions from all around the world.
تقدّم إليه أشخاص من جميع أنحاء العالم.
They use techniques that he's never heard of,
استخدموا تقنيات لم يسمع بها من قبل،
and for his half a million dollars in prize money,
و بالنسبة لجائزته النقدية البالغة نصف مليون دولار،
Rob McEwen finds 3.4 billion dollars worth of gold.
حصل روب ماكيوين على 3.4 مليار دولار قيمة الذهب.
The market value of his company
القيمة السوقية لشركته
goes from 90 million to 10 billion dollars,
تبدأ من 90 مليون إلى 10 مليار دولار،
and I can tell you, because he's my neighbor,
و أستطيع القول ، لأنه جاري،
he's a happy camper. (Laughter)
أنه جار سعيد. (ضحك)
You know, conventional wisdom says talent is inside, right?
كما تعلمون, الحكمة التقليدية تقول أن الموهبة توجد بالداخل، صحيح؟
Your most precious asset goes out the elevator every night.
تحاول أن تظهر أفضل ماعندك كل يوم.
He viewed talent differently.
لقد نظَر إلى الموهبة بشكل مختلف.
He wondered, who are their peers?
تسائل ، من نظرائهم؟
He should have fired his geology department, but he didn't.
كان ينبغي عليه أن يشعل النار في إدارة الجيولوجيا خاصته لكنه لم يفعل.
You know, some of the best submissions
هل تعلمون أن بعض أفضل المشاركات
didn't come from geologists.
لم تأتي من جيولوجيين.
They came from computer scientists, engineers.
أتت من مهندسين وعلماء حاسب آلي.
The winner was a computer graphics company
الرابح كان شركة لرسومات الحاسوب
that built a three dimensional model of the mine
التي قامت بإنشاء نموذج ثلاثي أبعاد للمنجم
where you can helicopter underground
حيث يمكنك أن تحوم في الأسفل
and see where the gold is.
وترى أين يوجد الذهب.
He helped us understand that social media's becoming
لقد ساعدنا في فهم أن وسائل الإعلام الإجتماعية أصبحت
social production.
إنتاج إجتماعي.
It's not about hooking up online.
الأمر لا يتعلق بالإرتباط عن طريق الإنترنت.
This is a new means of production in the making.
هذه وسيلة جديدة للإنتاج.
And this Ideagora that he created, an open market, agora,
و "ميدان الأفكار" الذي أنشأه ، سوق مفتوحة ، ميدان
for uniquely qualified minds,
للعقول البارعة المتفردة،
was part of a change, a profound change in the deep structure
كان جزءاً من تغيير، تغيير عميق في البنية العميقة
and architecture of our organizations,
و اسلوب البناء لمنظماتنا،
and how we sort of orchestrate capability to innovate,
و كيف يمكننا ضبط الموهبة لابتكار
to create goods and services,
و انتاج البضائع والخدمات،
to engage with the rest of the world,
و للتعامل مع بقية العالم،
in terms of government, how we create public value.
و في يتعلق بالسياسة ، كيف يمكننا خلق قيمة عامة.
Openness is about collaboration.
الإنفتاح يعني التعاون.
Now secondly, openness is about transparency.
الآن ثانياً, الإنفتاح يعني الشفافية.
This is different. Here, we're talking about the communication
هذا مختلف. نحن نتحدث هنا الآن عن نقل
of pertinent information to stakeholders of organizations:
المعلومات ذات الصلة إلى أصحاب المصلحة في المؤسسات:
employees, customers, business partners, shareholders,
الموظفين, العملاء, الشركاء , المساهمين
and so on.
و الخ...
And everywhere, our institutions are becoming naked.
و في كل مكان ، مؤسساتنا أصبحت مكشوفة.
People are all bent out of shape about WikiLeaks,
الناس مستائون من ويكيليكس,
but that's just the tip of the iceberg.
و لكن هذا ليس سوى غيض من فيض.
You see, people at their fingertips now, everybody,
كما ترون، أصبحوا في متناول يد الجميع الآن. و الجميع
not just Julian Assange,
ليس فقط جوليان أسانج،
have these powerful tools for finding out what's going on,
لديهم هذه الأدوات القوية لمعرفة ما يجري،
scrutinizing, informing others,
و للتقصي و إبلاغ الآخرين,
and even organizing collective responses.
و حتى لتنظيم استجابات جماعية.
Institutions are becoming naked,
أصبحت المؤسسات مكشوفة،
and if you're going to be naked,
وإن كنت ستصبح عارياً
well, there's some corollaries that flow from that.
فهناك بعض النتائج الطبيعية التي تنتج عن ذلك.
I mean, one is,
أعني أن،
fitness is no longer optional. (Laughter)
اللياقة البدنية لم تعد اختيارية. (ضحك)
You know? Or if you're going to be naked, you'd better get buff.
أنتم تعلمون. أو إن كنت ستصبح عارياً فمن الأفضل أن تصقل نفسك.
Now, by buff I mean, you need to have good value,
أعني بالصقل، أنك بحاجة لأن يكون لديك قيمة جيدة.
because value is evidenced like never before.
لأن القيمة أصبحت ظاهرة بشكل لم يسبق له مثيل.
You say you have good products.
أنت تقول أن لديك منتجات جيدة.
They'd better be good.
من اللازم أن تكون جيدة.
But you also need to have values.
لكنك أيضاً بحاجة إلى أن تمتلك قيم.
You need to have integrity as part of your bones
يجب أن تكون الإستقامة و النزاهة جزء منك
and your DNA as an organization,
و متشكلة فيك,
because if you don't, you'll be unable to build trust,
لأنك إن لم تكن تملكها ، فلن تكون قادراً على بناء الثقة،
and trust is a sine qua non of this new network world.
و الثقة شرط لا مناص منه في هذا العالم الرقمي الجديد.
So this is good. It's not bad.
و هذا أمر جيد ، ليس سيئاً.
Sunlight is the best disinfectant.
ضوء الشمس أفضل مطهر.
And we need a lot of sunlight in this troubled world.
و نحن بحاجة إلى الكثير من ضوء الشمس في هذا العالم المضطرب.
Now, the third meaning and corresponding principle
الآن ، المعنى الثالث و المبدأ المتوافق
of openness is about sharing.
مع الإنفتاح هو عن المشاركة.
Now this is different than transparency.
و هذا يختلف عن الشفافية.
Transparency is about the communication of information.
الشفافية تتعلق بنقل المعلومات.
Sharing is about giving up assets, intellectual property.
المشاركة تعني التخلي عن الممتلكات، الملكية الفكرية.
And there are all kinds of famous stories about this.
وهناك قصص شهيرة من كل الأنواع حول هذا الموضوع.
IBM gave away 400 million dollars of software
شركة آي بي إم أعطت 400 مليون دولار قيمة برمجيات
to the Linux movement, and that gave them
لحركة برنامج التشغيل لينكس ، وهذا أعطاهم
a multi-billion dollar payoff.
مكاسب بالمليارات.
Now, conventional wisdom says,
الحكمة التقليدية تقول :
"Well, hey, our intellectual property belongs to us,
" حسناً, ملكيتنا الفكرية هي ملك لنا،
and if someone tries to infringe it, we're going to get out
و إن حاول أحدٌ ما التعدي عليها، فإننا سنستدعي
our lawyers and we're going to sue them."
محامونا و سنقاضيهم. "
Well, it didn't work so well for the record labels, did it?
لم تعمل هذه الحكمة بشكل جيد مع شركات انتاج الموسيقى,أليس كذلك؟
I mean, they took — They had a technology disruption,
أعني أنهم أخذوا -- كان هناك تكنولوجيا هدّامة
and rather than taking a business model innovation
و بدلاً من ابتكار اسلوب عمل جديد
to correspond to that, they took and sought a legal solution
ليتوافق مع تلك التكنولوجيا ، اتخذوا وسعوا إلى حل قانوني
and the industry that brought you Elvis and the Beatles
و الصناعة التي جلبت لكم ألفيس و فرقة البيتلز
is now suing children
تقاضي الصغار الآن
and is in danger of collapse.
و هي معرضة للإنهيار.
So we need to think differently about intellectual property.
لذلك نحن بحاجة للتفكير بطريقة مختلفة في الملكية الفكرية.
I'll give you an example.
سأضرب لكم مثالاً.
The pharmaceutical industry is in deep trouble.
الصناعة الدوائية في مأزق عميق.
First of all, there aren't a lot of big inventions
أولاُ، لايوجد الكثير من الإبتكارات الكبرى
in the pipeline, and this is a big problem for human health,
في خط الإنتاج، وهذه مشكلة كبيرة فيما يتعلق بصحة الإنسان.
and the pharmaceutical industry has got a bigger problem,
والصناعات الدوائية تعاني من مشكلة أكبر،
that they're about to fall off something
حيث أنها على وشك السقوط
called the patent cliff.
في ما يسمّى بـ " هاوية براءات الإختراع ".
Do you know about this?
هل تعرفون عن هذا؟
They're going to lose 20 to 35 percent of their revenue
سوف تخسر بنسبة 20 إلى 35% من عائداتها
in the next 12 months.
في الإثني عشر شهراً القادمة.
And what are you going to do,
وماذا سوف نفعل،
like, cut back on paper clips or something? No.
خفض نفقات مشابك الورق أو شيئاً من هذا؟ لا!
We need to reinvent the whole model of scientific research.
نحن بحاجة إلى إعادة ابتكار اسلوب البحث العلمي بأكمله.
The pharmaceutical industry needs to place assets
على الصناعات الدوائية أن تضع ما عندها
in a commons. They need to start sharing precompetitive research.
بين يدي العامة. إنها بحاجة لبدء مشاركة البحوث التعاونية.
They need to start sharing
إنها بحاجة لبدء تبادل
clinical trial data,
بيانات التجارب السريرية,
and in doing so, create a rising tide that could lift all boats,
و عند ذلك ، ستتحقق الفائدة للجميع،
not just for the industry but
ليس فقط للصناعة
for humanity.
بل للإنسانية.
Now, the fourth meaning
الآن ، المعنى الرابع
of openness,
للإنفتاح،
and corresponding principle, is about empowerment.
و المبدأ المتوافق ، هو التمكين.
And I'm not talking about the motherhood sense here.
و أنا لا أتحدث عن معنى الأمومة هنا.
Knowledge and intelligence is power,
المعرفة والذكاء قوة،
and as it becomes more distributed, there's a
و بما أنها أصبحت موزعة أكثر، هناك
concomitant distribution
توزيع مصاحب
and decentralization and disaggregation of power
و لامركزية و انقسام للقوة
that's underway in the world today.
الموجودة في العالم اليوم.
The open world is bringing freedom.
العالم المنفتح يجلب الحرية.
Now, take the Arab Spring.
الآن، خذوا على سبيل المثال الربيع العربي.
The debate about the role of social media
لقد استقر النقاش حول دور وسائل الإعلام الإجتماعية
and social change has been settled.
و التغيير الإجتماعي.
You know, one word: Tunisia.
كما تعلمون ، كلمة واحدة: تونس،
And then it ended up having a whole bunch of other words too.
و انتهى الأمر بعد ذلك بوجود مجموعة كاملة من الكلمات الأخرى أيضاً.
But in the Tunisian revolution,
لكن في الثورة التونسية،
the new media didn't cause the revolution;
الإعلام الجديد لم يتسبب في الثورة،
it was caused by injustice.
الظلم هو من أحدث الثورة.
Social media didn't create the revolution;
وسائل الإعلام الإجتماعية لم تخلق الثورة،
it was created by a new generation of young people
من خلق الثورة هم جيل جديد من الشباب
who wanted jobs and hope and
الذين أرادوا الحصول على عمل و على أمل
who didn't want to be treated as subjects anymore.
و لم يعد يريدوا أن يتم التعامل معهم كرعية خاضعين.
But just as the Internet drops transaction and collaboration
لكن تماماً مثلما أسقط الإنترنت قيمة التعاملات التجارية
costs in business and government,
و التعاون في مجال السياسة والتجارة,
it also drops the cost of dissent, of rebellion,
أسقط كذلك قيمة الإنشقاق و التمرد
and even insurrection
و حتى العصيان المسلح
in ways that people didn't understand.
بطرق لم يفهمها الناس.
You know, during the Tunisian revolution,
أنتم تعلمون ، أنه أثناء الثورة التونسية,
snipers associated with the regime were killing
القناصة المتعاونون مع النظام كانوا يقتلون
unarmed students in the street.
طلاب غير مسلحين في الشارع.
So the students would take their mobile devices,
لذا فالطلاب كانوا يأخذون هواتفهم المحمولة
take a picture, triangulate the location,
و يلتقطون صورة ، و يحددون الموقع
send that picture to friendly military units,
و يرسلون تلك الصورة إلى وحدات عسكرية صديقة،
who'd come in and take out the snipers.
الذين يأتون بدورهم ويقضون على القناصة.
You think that social media is about hooking up online?
هل تعتقدون أن وسائل الإعلام الإجتماعية تعني الإرتباط عن طريق الإنترنت؟
For these kids, it was a military tool
بالنسبة لأولئك الصغار, كان الإنترنت وسيلة عسكرية
to defend unarmed people from murderers.
لحماية الغير مسلحين من المجرمين.
It was a tool of self-defense.
كان وسيلة للدفاع عن النفس.
You know, as we speak today, young people
كما تعلمون، بينما نتحدث الآن,
are being killed in Syria,
يوجد في سوريا شباب يُقتلون
and up until three months ago,
و منذ ثلاثة أشهر،
if you were injured on the street,
إن كنت مصاباً في الشارع،
an ambulance would pick you up,
ستقلّك سيارة إسعاف،
take you to the hospital, you'd go in, say, with a broken leg,
و تنقلك إلى المستشفى، ستدخل إلى هناك بساق مكسورة،
and you'd come out with a bullet in your head.
و ستخرج مصاباً بطلقة في رأسك.
So these 20-somethings created
كل تلك العشرين حالة خلقت
an alternative health care system,
نظام رعاية صحية بديل،
where what they did is they used Twitter and basic
حيث استخدموا تويتر و أدوات أساسية
publicly available tools that when someone's injured,
متاحة بشكل علني حيث عندما يصاب أحدٌ ما
a car would show up, it would pick them up,
تخرج سيارة وتقلّهم
take them to a makeshift medical clinic, where you'd get
وتأخذهم إلى عيادة طبية مؤقتة حيث
medical treatment, as opposed to being executed.
يتلقون العلاج بدلاً من أن يُعدموا.
So this is a time of great change.
إذن هذا هو وقت التغيير الكبير.
Now, it's not without its problems.
لكنه لا يخلو من المشاكل.
Up until two years ago,
في السابق وحتى السنتين الماضيتين،
all revolutions in human history had a leadership,
كان يوجد قادة لكل الثورات في التاريخ الإنساني,
and when the old regime fell, the leadership
و عندما يسقط النظام القديم, يتولى
and the organization would take power.
السلطة القادة والتنظيم.
Well, these wiki revolutions happen so fast
حسناً، تلك الثورات حدثت بسرعة كبيرة
they create a vacuum, and
و أحدثت فراغاً،
politics abhors a vacuum,
و السياسة تمقت الفراغ،
and unsavory forces can fill that,
و بإمكان القوى البغيضة أن تملأ ذلك الفراغ،
typically the old regime,
عادةً ما يملؤه النظام القديم,
or extremists, or fundamentalist forces.
أو المتطرفين أو القوى الأصولية.
You can see this playing out today in Egypt.
يمكنكم أن تروا هذا في مصر.
But that doesn't matter,
لكن هذا لا يهم,
because this is moving forward.
لأن هذا يمضي قدماً.
The train has left the station. The cat is out of the bag.
القطار غادر المحطة. خرجت القطة من الحقيبة.
The horse is out of the barn. Help me out here, okay?
خرج الحصان من الحظيرة. ساعدوني كي أخرج من هنا,اتفقنا؟
(Laughter) The toothpaste is out of the tube.
(ضحك) خرج معجون الأسنان من الأنبوب.
I mean, we're not putting this one back.
أعني أننا لا نُعيد الأمر إلى ماكان عليه في السابق.
The open world is bringing empowerment and freedom.
العالم المفتوح يجلب التمكين والحرية.
I think, at the end of these four days,
أعتقد، في نهاية هذه الأيام الأربعة.
that you'll come to conclude that the arc of history
أنكم ستتوصلون إلى أن قوس التاريخ
is a positive one, and it's towards openness.
هو قوس إيجابي ، وهو في طريقه نحو الإنفتاح.
If you go back a few hundred years,
لو رجعتم إلى الوراء لبضع مئات من السنين,
all around the world it was a very closed society.
كان العالم بأكمله مجتمع منغلق جداً
It was agrarian, and the means of production
كان مجتمعاً زراعياً ، و وسائل الإنتاج
and political system was called feudalism, and knowledge
و النظام السياسي كان يسمى " إقطاعي " ، والمعرفة
was concentrated in the church and the nobility.
كانت حكراً على الكنيسة وعلى طبقة النبلاء.
People didn't know about things.
كان الناس جهلة لا يعرفون شيئاً.
There was no concept of progress.
لم يكن هناك مفهوم للتقدم.
You were born, you lived your life and you died.
تُولد ثم تقضي حياتك ثم تموت.
But then Johannes Gutenberg came along with his great invention,
لكن بعد ذلك ظهر جونسون جيتنبرج باختراعه العظيم،
and, over time, the society opened up.
و مع مرور الوقت، أصبح العالم منفتحاً.
People started to learn about things, and when they did,
بدأ الناس يتعلمون، وعندما تعلموا
the institutions of feudal society appeared
بدأت مؤسسات المجتمع الإقطاعي
to be stalled, or frozen, or failing.
بالتوقف أو التجمد أو الفشل.
It didn't make sense for the church to be responsible
لم يعد منطقياً أن تكون الكنيسة مسؤولة
for medicine when people had knowledge.
عن الطب عندما أمتلك الناس المعرفة.
So we saw the Protestant Reformation.
فرأينا الإصلاح البروتستانتي.
Martin Luther called the printing press
كان مارتن لوثر يدعو المطبعة بـأنها
"God's highest act of grace."
" أكبر نعم الله "
The creation of a corporation, science, the university,
ظهور الشركات، والعلم ، و الجامعات
eventually the Industrial Revolution,
و أخيراً الثورة الصناعية،
and it was all good.
كلها كانت أمور جيدة.
But it came with a cost.
لكن كان لظهورها ثمن.
And now, once again, the technology genie
و الآن ، مرة أخرى ، خرج المارد التقني
is out of the bottle, but this time it's different.
من زجاجته ، لكن الوضع مختلف هذه المرة.
The printing press gave us access to the written word.
أوصلتنا المطبعة للكلمة المكتوبة.
The Internet enables each of us to be a producer.
شبكة الإنترنت مكّنت كل واحد منا ليكون منتجاً.
The printing press gave us access to recorded knowledge.
أوصلتنا المطبعة للمعرفة المسجلة.
The Internet gives us access,
الإنترنت أتاح لنا الوصول،
not just to information and knowledge, but
ليس فقط للمعلومات والمعرفة ، بل أيضاً
to the intelligence contained in the crania of other people
للذكاء الموجود في عقول الآخرين
on a global basis.
على مستوى عالمي.
To me, this is not an information age,
بالنسبة لي ، هذا العصر ليس عصر المعلومات،
it's an age of networked intelligence.
إنه عصر الذكاء الشبكي.
It's an age of vast promise,
إنه عصر مبشر بخير عظيم،
an age of collaboration,
إنه عصر التعاون،
where the boundaries of our organizations are changing,
حيث تتغير فيه حدود منظماتنا،
of transparency, where sunlight
هو عصر الشفافية، حيث يُطهر
is disinfecting civilization,
ضوء الشمس الحضارة،
an age of sharing and understanding
هو عصر المشاركة وإدراك
the new power of the commons,
القوة الجديدة لعامة الناس،
and it's an age of empowerment
و هو عصر التمكين
and of freedom.
و الحرية.
Now, what I'd like to do is,
و الآن، ما أود فعله هو
to close, to share with you
أن أنتهي ، وأن أشارككم
some research that I've been doing.
بعض أبحاثي التي كنت أجريها.
I've tried to study all kinds of organizations
حاولت أن أبحث في كل أنواع المنظمات
to understand what the future might look like,
كي أستنتج كيف يمكن أن يكون شكل المستقبل،
but I've been studying nature recently.
لكنني مؤخراً أصبحت أدرس الطبيعة.
You know, bees come in swarms
كما تعلمون ، النحل يأتي في شكل أسراب
and fish come in schools.
والسمك يأتي في شكل أفواج.
Starlings, in the area around Edinburgh,
طيور الزرازير,في المنطقة الواقعة حول أدنبرة،
in the moors of England,
في مستنقعات انجلترا،
come in something called a murmuration,
تقوم بما يسمى بـ " الهمهمة "،
and the murmuration refers to the murmuring of the wings
و الهمهمة تشير إلى حفيف أجنحة
of the birds, and throughout the day the starlings
الطيور، وخلال اليوم تقوم طيور الزرازير
are out over a 20-mile radius
على مدى أكثر من 20 ميلاً
sort of doing their starling thing.
بعمل هذه الهمهمة.
And at night they come together
و في الليل، تجتمع هذه الطيور
and they create one of the most spectacular things
وتقوم بصنع واحد من أكثر الأشياء المدهشة
in all of nature,
في الطبيعة كلها،
and it's called a murmuration.
وهو يسمى بالهمهمة.
And scientists that have studied this have said
وقد قال العلماء الذين درسوا هذه الظاهرة
they've never seen an accident.
أنهم لم يروا أي إصطدام أو حادثة بين الطيور من قبل.
Now, this thing has a function.
الآن ، هذا العمل له مهمة.
It protects the birds.
إنه يحمي الطيور.
You can see on the right here,
وعلى اليمين هنا,يمكنكم رؤية
there's a predator being chased away by the collective power
طائر مفترس تطارده القوة الجماعية
of the birds, and apparently this is a frightening thing
لهذه الطيور, وكما هو واضح هذا شيء مخيف
if you're a predator of starlings.
إن كنت المفترس الذي يفترس طيور الزرازير.
And there's leadership,
هناك قيادة،
but there's no one leader.
لكن لا يوجد قائد.
Now, is this some kind of fanciful analogy,
والآن ، هل هذا نوع من التشبيه الخيالي،
or could we actually learn something from this?
أم أننا بالفعل يمكن أن نتعلم شيئاً من هذا؟
Well, the murmuration functions to record
حسناً ، وظائف الهمهمة تشير إلى
a number of principles,
عدد من المبادئ،
and they're basically the principles that
وهي في الأساس المبادئ
I have described to you today.
التي شرحتها لكم اليوم.
This is a huge collaboration.
هذا تعاون ضخم.
It's an openness, it's a sharing
إنه انفتاح، مشاركة
of all kinds of information, not just about location
بكافة أنواع المعلومات، ليس فقط عن الموقع
and trajectory and danger and so on, but about food sources.
والمسار والخطر وما إلى ذلك، بل أيضاً عن مصادر الغذاء.
And there's a real sense of interdependence,
و هناك معنى حقيقي للإعتماد المتبادل,
that the individual birds somehow understand
حيث تفهم بعض الطيور بطريقة ما
that their interests are in the interest of the collective.
أن مصلحتها في مصلحة الجماعة.
Perhaps like we should understand
ربما علينا أن نفهم
that business can't succeed
أن المهمة لا يمكن أن تنجح
in a world that's failing.
في هذا العالم المتخاذل.
Well, I look at this thing,
نظرت إلى هذا الشيء،
and I get a lot of hope.
و امتلات روحي بأملٍ كبير.
Think about the kids today in the Arab Spring, and
فكروا بالصغار اليوم في الربيع العربي
you see something like this that's underway.
و سترون شيئاً مماثلاً لما يجري هنا.
And imagine, just consider this idea, if you would:
و تخيلوا، فقط تأملوا في هذه الفكرة إن أردتم:
What if we could connect ourselves in this world
ماذا لو تواصلنا مع بعضنا البعض في هذا العالم
through a vast network of air and glass?
من خلال شبكة هائلة من الهواء والزجاج؟
Could we go beyond just sharing information and knowledge?
هل يمكن أن نتجاوز مجرد التشارك بالمعلومات والمعرفة؟
Could we start to share our intelligence?
هل يمكن أن نتشارك ذكائنا؟
Could we create some kind of
هل يمكن أن نخلق نوعاً من
collective intelligence
الذكاء الجماعي
that goes beyond an individual or a group or a team
الذي يتجاوز الفرد أو المجموعة أو الفريق
to create, perhaps, some kind of consciousness
هل يمكن أن نخلق نوع من وعي
on a global basis?
على مستوى عالمي؟
Well, if we could do this, we could attack some big problems in the world.
لو تمكنا من فعل هذا ، سنتمكن من مواجهة مشاكل كبيرة في العالم.
And I look at this thing,
و أنظر إلى هذا الشيء
and, I don't know, I get a lot of hope that maybe this
و لا أدري ، لكن يملأني أمل بأن
smaller, networked, open world
العالم الأصغر الشبكي المفتوح
that our kids inherit might be a better one, and that
الذي يسكنه صغارنا قد يكون عالماً أفضل،
this new age of networked intelligence could be
و أن عصر الذكاء الشبكي الجديد هذا قد يكون
an age of promise fulfilled
عصر الوعد المُحقق
and of peril unrequited.
و الأمن المتبادل.
Let's do this. Thank you.
لنفعل هذا. شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)